Guide to the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records WAG.131
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records
1927, 1935-2006, 2009-ongoing
1960-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2
WAG.131
11.5 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 6 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 5 folders in 1 shared oversize box
19 videocassettes
3 websites in 3 archived websites.
The Utility Workers Union of America Local 1-2 represents members working in the electric, gas, water, and nuclear industries in the New York area, with the bulk of their members employed by ConEd. Local 1-2 evolved out of the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1938. The collection documents the origins of the Local and its expansion to include employees at companies other than ConEd; elections of officers and of changes to bylaws; various political parties within the Local, including the Justice Party, Members 1st Party, New Directions Caucus, Administration, and the Unity Party; and the planning of strikes and positions taken by different political parties within the Local on the strike or possibility of the strike, as well as picket duty lists, schedules, and photographs of demonstrations and rallies. These materials date from 1927 to 2004, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1960s to late 1990s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 sent a gift of four linear feet of materials in 1997-1998. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1997.063 and 1997.064.
Additional materials were donated by the Utility Workers Union of America (UWUA), Local 1-2 in 2003. The accession number associated with this accretion is 2016.001.
UWUA, Local 1-2 President James Slevin sent an additional donation of UWUA videos in 2014. The union also sent a donation of a scrapbook, and a small amount of organizing records around this time. The accession number associated with these gifts is 2017.042.
The accession number NPA 2001.026 is also associated with this collection.
https://uwua1-2.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2009 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In September 2021, https://www.youtube.com/user/uwualocal12/videos/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.015. In September 2023, https://www.youtube.com/@uwualocal12/videos/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.080.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Historical Note
The Utility Workers Union of America Local 1-2 represents members working in the electric, gas, water, and nuclear industries in the New York area, with the bulk of their members employed by ConEd. Local 1-2 evolved out of the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1938.
From the mid-1930s, the employees in the New York utility industry had company unions, which were easily controlled by management. In 1937, the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW), an American Federation of Labor (AFL) affiliate, obtained the right to represent the Consolidated Edison (ConEd) employees through a consent recognition, rather than through an election of the employees. The IBEW issued charters to the seven company unions: two charters were issued to ConEd employees; the third went to the New York Steam employees; the fourth to Consolidated Telegraph & Electrical Subway employees; the fifth to New York and Queens Electric Light and Power employees; the sixth to Brooklyn Edison Company employees; and the seventh to the employees of two Westchester affiliates. The members of Locals 1 and 2 were not happy with their new union as the IBEW chartered them as "B" locals, meaning the members could not perform work that the IBEW reserved for its "A" members, who were not ConEd employees.
In 1940, the ConEd employees withdrew from the IBEW and the seven chartered locals formed the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees (BCEE), which was independent from the AFL and the CIO. After winning an election ordered and conducted by the National Labor Relations Board, the BCEE took the name Local 1-2, representing the separate identities of two major categories within ConEd, plant and clerical workers, and eventually came to represent all unionized workers at ConEd.
In 1945, Local 1-2 accepted an invitation to become part of the UWOC. A year later the UWOC became the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO with more than 225 locals organized nationwide. Throughout its history, the Local has had a contentious relationship with ConEd, particularly over contract negotiations. Negotiations would often result in strikes. One nine-week strike in 1983 resulted in losses for the Local and widespread dissatisfaction with the Local leadership among members.
There have been a number of power struggles within the Local, between a number of officers and political parties. One of the major points of contention was the trusteeship instituted by the National in 1998 due to alleged mismanagement of funds by the president of the Local, Joseph Flaherty. The Members 1st party backed the trustee, James Keller, while the Justice Party wanted to gain control of the Local back from the National.
Scope and Content Note
The Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Records document the history of the Local from its beginnings as an employee representation plan for Consolidated Edison employees to a modern Local representing workers at ConEd and other companies in the electric, gas, water, and nuclear industries across the New York area. The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, and minutes documenting the origins of the Local and its expansion to include employees at companies other than ConEd. These materials date from 1927 to 2004, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1960s to late 1990s.
Elections of officers and of changes to the Local's bylaws are documented through correspondence, notices, posters, polling lists, and election results. These include materials documenting the 1940 election which resulted in the creation of Local 1-2 as a separate local representing ConEd workers.
Contract negotiations from the origins of Local 1-2 through the 2000s are well documented. Negotiations surrounding the creation of Local 1-2 in 1940 include correspondence and memoranda between the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees, Consolidated Edison Company of New York, and the National Labor Relations Board. Contract negotiations from the late 1950s through the early 2000s are documented through minutes of the negotiations; issues of Bargaining Bulletin, The Record, and Utility Workers' Light; handbooks on mobilizing members; and surveys of union members regarding where they work and what issues in the contract are important to them.
Materials related to strikes include correspondence, newsletters, notices, and posters regarding planning of strikes and positions taken by different political parties within the Local on the strike or possibility of the strike, as well as picket duty lists, schedules, and photographs of demonstrations and rallies. The strikes that took place in the early 1990s are well documented through picket duty lists, schedules, and newsletters.
Struggles between various political parties within the Local are documented through notices, posters, and newsletters, with a large portion documenting the clash between the Members 1st Party and the Justice Party over the trusteeship of the Local. Other political parties represented include the New Directions Caucus, Administration, and the Unity Party.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into eight series, one of which is divided into subseries: Series I: Bylaws and Constitutions; Series II: Minutes; Series III: Correspondence; Series IV: Election Records; Series V: Bargaining and Negotiation Records: Subseries V.A: 1997 accession; Subseries V.B: Contracts; Subseries V.C: Grievance Files; Subseries V.D: Mergers; Subseries V.E: Strikes; Series VI: General Files; Series VII: Archived Websites; and Series VIII: Conferences and Conventions Files. Material from the original processing in 1997 is listed first in each series with material from an accession received in 2003 listed after, with the exception of Series V which has been divided into subseries, with subseries V.A. containing bargaining records from the 1997 accession and subseries V.B. through V.E. containing bargaining records from the 2003 accession. Series I is arranged chronologically through the 1997 accession and then alphabetically by organization and chronologically within each organization; II-IV are arranged chronologically; within Series V, subseries V.A., V.B., V.E. are arranged chronologically and subseries V.C. and V.D. are arranged alphabetically; and series VI and VIII are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The Record, the newspaper of Local 1-2. Call number HD6350.P88 R43.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Separated Material
Six linear feet of photographs were separated from this collection and are now in the Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2 Photographs collection, collection number PHOTOS.118.
Appraisal
The 2003 accretion included a large number of duplicates of notices of elections, strikes, and positions taken by different political parties within Local 1-2; newspaper clippings; and publications by the Local, the national union, and conventions, which were weeded. These materials constituted five linear feet of material.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Collective labor agreements -- Public utilities.; Strikes and lockouts -- Public utilities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Financial records; Arbitration, Industrial.; Fliers (printed matter); Labor unions -- Elections -- New York (State) -- New York.; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions.; Bylaws (administrative records); Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (N.Y.); Audiovisual materials.; Videocassettes.; Audiocassettes.; Photographs.; Constitutions.; Ballots.; Posters.; Clippings (information artifacts); Election returns.; Correspondence.; Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; American Federation of Labor; Consolidated Edison Company of New York, inc.; Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; Utility Workers Organizing Committee; United States. National Labor Relations Board; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Utility Workers Union of America. Local 1-2
- Series I: Bylaws, 1942-2001; 0.2 Linear Feet in 8 file folders and 1 oversize folder
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically through the 1997 accession and then alphabetically by organization and chronologically within each organization.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains originals and photocopies of bylaws and proposed bylaws of Local 1-2, the Joint Council of Locals 1-2 and 4, and the Joint Council of the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees; a small amount of correspondence between Joseph A. Fisher, National President, and Edward M. O'Keefe, Secretary-Treasurer of Local 1-2, concerning changes to the Local's bylaws; correspondence and notices reflecting the use of bylaw changes by dissident groups within Local 1-2 to effect alterations in structure and leadership; and copies of the constitution of the Utility Workers Union of America.
  - Bylaws: Proposed Amendments, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bylaws: Proposed Amendments, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bylaws: Proposed Amendments, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bylaws: Proposed Amendments, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Local 1-2 bylaws, 1942-1961 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 1, Box 4)
  - Local 1-2 bylaws, 1987-2001 (Box 4, Folder 2, Box 11)
  - Joint Councils bylaws, 1952, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Utility Workers Union of America constitution, 1946-1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II: Minutes, 1963-1989; 0.7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of meeting and chronologically by year within that arrangement.
  This series and is divided into two parts: minutes of Executive Board meetings and minutes of General Membership meetings, each of which reflects the varied political concerns (both internal and external), industrial issues, and bargaining points confronting the Local over the past three decades.
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1964 January 1-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1964 June 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1965 January 1-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1965 June 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1966 January 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1966 July 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1967 January 1-May 31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1967 June 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1968 January 1-August 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1968 September 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1974 January 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1974 July 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1989 January 1-June 30 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1989 July 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Minutes - Executive Board, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Minutes -Membership Meetings, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1939-2002; 0.1 Linear Feet in 7 folders
  Material from the 1997 accession is arranged alphabetically by type of correspondence and chronologically within that arrangement. Material from the 2003 accretion is arranged chronologically by year.
  Most of the officers' correspondence has not been preserved. This series includes routine memoranda and publicity communications between the National Union, regional offices, and the Local; a very small amount of correspondence between Marshall M. Hicks, National Secretary-Treasurer, and different officers of the Local regarding financial transactions and creation of working papers; correspondence between members of the National, including Joseph A. Fisher, President, and Harold J. Straub, Vice President, and Oliver J. Harper, an attorney contracted to represent the National.
  - Correspondence: Officers, 1960-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, Region 1, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence: UWUA, Region 1, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - General correspondence, 1939-2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Election Records, 1940-2002; 0.7 Linear Feet in 22 file folders and 2 oversize folders
  This series is arranged chronologically by year.
  This series documents the contentious election history of the Local. Elections are well represented through leaflets, memos, clippings, ballot tallies, and official reports of arbitrators and court-appointed monitors. This series contains correspondence and memoranda between the locals, the companies, and the National Labor Relations Board regarding the planning of elections; notices of elections and election results; decisions of the National Labor Relations Board; notices with platforms and election slates for political parties within Local 1-2, including the Justice Party, the Unity Party, Members 1st Party, and Administration; lists of election observers; notices and posters for elections; polling lists; and election results. Correspondents include the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees; the Joint Council of Locals 1, 2, 3, 4, and 7; Consolidated Edison System Companies; Harold J. Straub; Elinore M. Herrick; Patrick McGrath; Augustus Low; Andrew McMahon; John C. Arnell; Edward L. Marsine; and Bernard E. Gallagher. Early elections are well represented, especially the 1940 election in which the Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison Employees became Local 1-2.
  - Election, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Election, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Election, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Election, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Election, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Election, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Election, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Election, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Election (I), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Election (II), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Election, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1940-2002 (Box 4, Folder 6-16)
  - Elections, 1940-1949, 1974, 1986-1992, 2002 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 1-2)
- Series V: Bargaining Records, 1935-2002, undated; 3.4 Linear Feet in 3 and a half record cartons, 2 oversize folders, 1 D-2 cassette, 1 VHS cassette, and 3 buttons
  This series is divided into the following subseries: Subseries V.A: 1997 accession; Subseries V.B: Contracts; Subseries V.C: Grievance Files; Subseries V.D: Mergers; and Subseries V.E: Strikes.
  This series contains correspondence, memoranda, minutes, booklets, pamphlets, notices, posters, VHS cassettes, and photographs documenting aspects of the Local's role in bargaining and negotiating on behalf of its members.
  - Subseries V.A: 1997 accession, 1958-1993; 1.3 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 10 folders
    This subseries is arranged by document type and then chronologically by year within that arrangement.
    This subseries documents the major points of contention between ConEd and Local 1-2 through bargaining files, agreements and arbitration awards and reflect the continuing pressure from dissident groups against the leadership of the Local. Documents include leaflets, typescript memoranda, and reports calling on members to reject various packages proposed by the Local leadership.
    - Bargaining, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bargaining (I), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bargaining (II), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bargaining (III), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bargaining (IV), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bargaining (Settlement), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bargaining (I), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bargaining (II), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bargaining (III), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bargaining (IV), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bargaining (V), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bargaining (I), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Bargaining (II), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Bargaining (III), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Bargaining, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Bargaining, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bargaining, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Bargaining, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Bargaining, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Bargaining, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bargaining, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Bargaining, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Agreement, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Agreement, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Arbitrations (I), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Arbitrations (II), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Arbitrations, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Arbitrations, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Arbitrations (I), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Arbitrations (II), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Arbitrations (I), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Arbitrations (II), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Arbitrations, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Arbitrations, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Arbitrations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Arbitrations, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Arbitrations, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Arbitrations, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)